<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The spring A sermon preached before the Prince at S. Iames, on Mid-lent Sunday last. By Daniel Price, chapleine in ordinarie to the Prince, and Master of Artes of Exeter Colledge in Oxford.</title>
            <author>Price, Daniel, 1581-1631.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1609</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10060</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20305</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115203</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850422</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850422</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15624</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10060)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15624)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1358:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The spring A sermon preached before the Prince at S. Iames, on Mid-lent Sunday last. By Daniel Price, chapleine in ordinarie to the Prince, and Master of Artes of Exeter Colledge in Oxford.</title>
                  <author>Price, Daniel, 1581-1631.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by John Windet] for Roger Iackson, and are to bee sold at his shop in Fleetestreete, fast by the Conduit,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1609.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A²  B-D⁴ E² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15624:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15624:1"/>
            <p>THE SPRING. A SERMON PREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHED BEFORE THE PRINCE AT S. IAMES,
<hi>On Mid-lent Sunday LAST.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By DANIEL PRICE, Chapleine in ordinarie to the <hi>PRINCE,</hi> and Maſter of Artes of EXETER Colledge in <hi>OXFORD.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>MATTH. 3.8.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Bring foorth fruit worthy amendement of life.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON Printed for <hi>Roger Iackſon,</hi> and are to bee ſold at his Shop in Fleeteſtreete, faſt by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duit. 1609.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15624:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15624:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable Lord, worthy the confluence of all Honours, ROBERT Earle of Salisburie, Lord High <hi>Treaſurer of ENGLAND, one of the</hi> Oracles of his Maieſties moſt Honourable Priuie Counſell, Knight of the moſt illuſtrious order of the GARTER, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſt Noble Lord, this Sermon the <hi>Spring,</hi> preached in the <hi>Spring garden</hi> of this land, the <hi>Princes Court,</hi> is offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to your Honourable Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance and Patronage. It is a free-will offering, <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruance</hi> did appoint it, <hi>Zeale</hi> did kindle it,
<hi>Study</hi> did enflame it, <hi>Pietie</hi> did ſacrifice it, and now
<hi>duetie</hi> doth offer it. The aboundant fruitfulneſse of your
<hi>Lordſhippe</hi> doth chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge this from all other, both for your ableneſſe and willingneſſe to good workes, wherein you
<pb facs="tcp:15624:3"/>beatifie your ſelfe, and beautifie this Land: the Lord reward you according to your harts deſire: He that hath them hath bleſſed your Honour with the <hi>Treaſures</hi> of wiſedome and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and hath giuen you the <hi>heart</hi> of prudence, the
<hi>eye</hi> of prouidence, the <hi>eare</hi> of iuſtice, the <hi>heart</hi> of Religion, and the <hi>ſpirite</hi> of deuotion, and hath made your Honour a moſt ſpeciall nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing father of his two deare Daughters, this
<hi>Church</hi> and <hi>common wealth.</hi> Ride on with your Honour, becauſe of the worde of <hi>truth,</hi> of <hi>meekeneſſe</hi> and
<hi>righteouſneſſe,</hi> and the Lord ſhall bee with you, and ſhall bleſſe you with the Grace of Glory here and the glory of Grace hence. And ſo in all obſeruance I reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>To be commaunded by your Lordſhippe. DANIEL PRICE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:15624:3"/>
            <head>THE SPRING</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>MATH. 3.8.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Bring forth fruit worthy amendment of life.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Yeare the Circle of time is ſo intorteled, as that
<hi>Annus</hi> is become <hi>Annulus,</hi> for one day telleth another, and one night certifieth another, that all things are in a Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and time that conſumeth all things, is it ſelfe conſumed. In the Generall diſtinction of Seaſons, <hi>(Salomon the Prince of Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers)</hi> accommodated a time, not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an oportune time to euery thing, and among the reſt, a time to plant, and a time to plucke vp that which is planted. <hi>Nyſſenus</hi> followeth the Allego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, <hi>God</hi> our father is the husbandman, <hi>Wee</hi> are his husbandry, the <hi>Soule</hi> is the ground, the <hi>Seede</hi> is the word. The <hi>Preachers</hi> do plant, <hi>Baptiſme</hi> doth
<pb facs="tcp:15624:4"/>water, the <hi>Spirit</hi> is the Winde,
<hi>Repentance</hi> is the Dewe, and <hi>Chriſt</hi> the Sunne of righteouſneſſe is the Sunne, and as in Nature, ſo in Grace, there is a Winter and Summer, a fall and <hi>Spring,</hi> a time of planting and a time of ſupplanting: At that ſeaſon of the yeare, I haue already handled the
<hi>Fall of the Leafe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">At Richmond October. 1
1608.</note> as I doubt not but this high and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable preſence doe remember, and therefore now I haue choſen out a Text fit for this ſeaſon the opening of the yeare, the flouring of the figge tree, the blooming of the Lilly, the budding of fruit, the flouriſhing of Flowers, and the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of all thoſe buried hearbes, <hi>whoſe honour lay in the duſt,</hi> vntill the Spring had againe appar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relled the earth with various and glorious orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. It was the ſpringing voyce of the ſpring, (who was
<hi>Oriens eximo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Oriens ex alto</hi>) in the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles: Ariſe my loue, my faire one, and come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, for behold Winter is paſt, the raine is gone away, the flowers appeare in the earth, the time of the ſinging of birdes is come, the voyce of the Turtle is heard in our land, the Figge tree hath brought foorth her young ſigges, and the vines with their ſmall grapes haue caſt a ſauour: Ariſe my Doue, my Loue, my faire one, and come away.<note place="margin">Pliny S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>linus.</note> The voyce of the
<hi>Turtle</hi> as the <hi>Naturaliſt</hi> obſerueth, is a mourning voyce,
<hi>Turtur non canit ſed gemit;</hi> The Turtle ſingeth not, but mourneth,
<hi>Quid per turturem niſi Eccleſia, quid per terram ſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi, niſi vitailla beata deſignatur?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. mag. in Cantica.</note> What is meant by the Doue but the voice of the Church, what
<pb facs="tcp:15624:4"/>by the land of the Spouſe, but the life of the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed? (ſayth <hi>Gregory</hi>): we haue already heard the loud voyce of <hi>Iohn,</hi> the voyce of the beloued <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> the moning voyce of the Church, the mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning voice of the <hi>Turtle,</hi> &amp; I hope the crying voyce of <hi>Iohn</hi> hath begot the weeping voyce of the Church in you, that ſo hauing beene planted and watered, now Gods graces in you may bee increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and you may <hi>bring forth fruit worthy amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Man was once placed in <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> now
<hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe</hi> is placed in man, <hi>Praedeſtination, Vocation, Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, Glorification,</hi> bee the foure Riuers of Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe: the vnderſtanding is the tree of knowledge, <hi>Beliefe</hi> the tree of life: In the fall after the Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, there was an Angell with a flaming ſword ſet to keepe out man; now there is an Angell, ſet in man to keepe out Sathan, the Angell is Chriſt, &amp; the ſword the worde, and the adminiſtration of the word: hee vſeth this ſword, ſometimes as a pruning knife, as in the
<hi>Canticles;</hi> ſometimes an <hi>axe,</hi> as in <hi>Mathew, Euery tree that bringeth not forth good fruit ſhall bee hewen downe and caſt into the fire.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 3.10.</note>
            </p>
            <p>It was the Proclamation of <hi>Ieremie, O Earth, Earth, Earth, heare the voyce of the Lord:</hi> I may ioyne my Text with that Proclamation: and as <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiel</hi> was ſent to Preach to drie bones,<note place="margin">Ier. 31.</note> and <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> to the drie deſart, and <hi>Ieremy</hi> to the drie earth, ſo may I ſay to the drie, empty, bare, barren de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſart, deſolate hearts of vnfruitfull hearers, O earth, earth, earth, bring foorth fruites worthy amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:15624:5"/>of life. <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> here ſeeth the Phariſies heape together to heare him, and knowing that they came hypocritically onely to heare, hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth that they alſo belieue, and beleeuing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, and profeſſing practiſe, and ſo bring foorth fruit worthy amendment of life.</p>
            <p>Be not dead or withered, or barren or harde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, for that is feareful and acurſed, but bring forth, not buddes nor bloſſomes, nor flowres nor flouriſhes, for theſe may be fained, but bring forth fruits, not the fruits of the world, they be but fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyes, or the fruits of the fleſh, they bee but folly, not the fruit of honour, it is but pompous folly, not the fruit of ſtrength, it is glorious vanity, not the fruites of pleaſures, they bee voluptuous ſenſuality, not the fruit of riches, they are immanent incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, not the fruits of long life, it is but tranſient mutability.</p>
            <p>Worthy fruites, worthy not of earthly prayſe or of worldly prize, but that high hopefull, holy, liuely, happy, heauenly calling of amendment of life; Bring forth fruites worthy amendment of life.</p>
            <p>Firſt a <hi>Production,</hi> bring forth, ſecond, a
<hi>Fructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication,</hi> fruit,<note place="margin">Diuiſion.</note> third, the <hi>fruites perfection,</hi> fruit wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy amendment. The firſt againſt barrenneſſe, the ſecond againſt weakeneſſe, the third againſt Phariſaicall <hi>Fainedneſſe.</hi> The firſt common to all Creatures,
<hi>to bring forth,</hi> the ſecond proper to the beſt Creatures, <hi>to bring forth fruit,</hi> the third moſt proper, and onely proper to the beſt
<hi>Chriſtians,
<pb facs="tcp:15624:5"/>fruit worthy amendment of life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is truely obſerued that the Spirituall <hi>Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> of the Soule is ſhadowed in the firſt creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the worlde: The
<hi>Chaos</hi> in Praedeſtination,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Part.</hi>
               </note> the ſeparating of light from darkeneſſe in Vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the creating of the Soule in Iuſtification, the framing of <hi>Adam</hi> in Glorification: In the firſt, there is the depth of Gods foreknowledge, a darke forme that cannot bee diſcerned. In the ſecond, Knowledge is ſeparated from ignorance, the light from darkeneſſe. In the third, the bright beames of Grace ſhine in the heart the Sun is created: In the fourth the image of God is plac't in the
<hi>Paradiſe</hi> of immortall ioy, onely,<note place="margin">Auſten.</note> this is the difference at the firſt, God placed <hi>Adam</hi> in
<hi>Paradiſe</hi> before hee did appoint him to worke, but now he appointeth him to worke before he placed him in <hi>Paradiſe.</hi> For when God had made a <hi>Paradiſe</hi> vpon earth, he tooke the man and put him into it, to digge it and keepe it, not enioyning him to beſtow any bodily labour in dreſſing it at that time, for that was his future puniſhment, but as
<hi>Ambroſe</hi> obſerueth, <hi>Quia pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus homo lex poſteritatis futurus erat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ambroſe.</note> 
               <hi>legitimi etiam in Paradiſo ſpeciem labor is ſuſcepit:</hi> Becauſe the firſt man was to be a liuing law to poſteritie, therefore euen in Paradiſe hee tooke a ſhew of labour. A labour and no labour, hee had the pleaſure of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, but not the labour of pleaſure, Paradiſe was his Pallace, all the world his Demaines, the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures his Subiectes,, the Angels his ſeruants.</p>
            <p>And he dreſſed and kept Paradiſe, as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth
<pb facs="tcp:15624:6"/>onely by keeping thoſe good graces which God had giuen him, and encreaſing them conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually: for <hi>O Ecumenius</hi> addeth this reaſon, that the graces of God,<note place="margin">O ecumenius.</note> as the flowers of a garden muſt not onely bee kept, but alſo be dreſſed, that they may haue not onely a beeing, but an abounding, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a man may haue great good things beeing in him, and yet be himſelfe a Garden, that is kept in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, but not dreſſed, and ſo bee altogether vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitfull: for though S. <hi>Bernards</hi> poſition in ſome things bee true,<note place="margin">Bernard.</note> 
               <hi>Praeſtat eſse Concham quam canalem,</hi> it is better to bee a Ceſterne then a ſluſe (and yet hereby many offend in retiring their labours, as wel as others in obtruding them) yet in Chriſtianity, <hi>Prestat eſſe Canalem quam Concham:</hi> It is better to bee a ſluſe then a Ceſterne, for that light is no light that is not ſeene before men, that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is no knowledge that is not imparted, that wiſedome is no wiſedome that is not diſcerned: that faith is bare faith which is not exerciſed, that ſeed is barren ſeed that is not fructified, for vnleſſe Chriſtians bring forth, they are idle and vnfruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in the knowledge of Chriſt. <hi>Apelles</hi> could make Artificiall Grapes,
<hi>Archimides</hi> an Artificial flying Doue, the <hi>Alchimiſt</hi> of making artificiall men, but all their birthes be abortiue.</p>
            <p>When God had ordained a Church at the firſt, this was his appointment, that ſhee ſhould fructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie and bring forth, and therefore ordered her that ſhee ſhould bee euer encreaſed by her owne af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions,

<pb facs="tcp:15624:6"/>perfited by her perſecutions, erected by her owne dilapidations,<note place="margin">Hilar lib. <hi>4.</hi> de Trinit.</note> by her owne teares her thirſt ſhould bee quenched, by her faſting ſhee ſhould be refreſhed, and by the bloud of her Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, her vineyeard ſhould bee watered. In the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer time of his Church, hee watered her with the bloud of <hi>beaſtes,</hi> but in the latter time by the bloud of men, making <hi>white Lillies</hi> to become <hi>red roſes:</hi> and then hee promiſed to make ſinners that were as <hi>red as ſcarlet as white as ſnow;</hi> now hee hath made ſome ſeruants that were white as ſnow, to bee by Martyrdome <hi>red as ſcarlet,</hi> and in the time of loue hath required more ſacrifices then in the time of the law hee had ſacrificed beaſts, becauſe as Saint <hi>Ierome</hi> obſerueth in his Epiſtle
<hi>ad Heliodorum,</hi> that for euery day of the yeare, euen in his time,<note place="margin">Jerom. ad Helio</note> there were fiue thouſand Martyres which had ſhed their bloud for the truth; hee that watered his Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yearde plentifully with the ſpringes of <hi>Caleb,</hi> ſprings beneath, the ſpringes of the bloud of the Saints; and ſpringes aboue, the moſt pure and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious ſprings of the bloud of his Sonne: how doth hee expect that this vineyeard ſhould bring foorth fruit in due ſeaſon, and as
<hi>Eſay</hi> ſpeaketh, how hath hee hedged, and gathered out the ſtones of it, and planted it with the beſt plants,<note place="margin">Iſai.
5.2.</note> and built a towre in the midſt thereof and made a Wine-preſſe therein, and looked that it ſhould bring forth. When hee made the world, he bad that the earth ſhould bring forth; and when hee made the waters, let the waters bring forth: and ſo to the Fowles,<note place="margin">Gen. 1.</note> and to the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes,
<pb facs="tcp:15624:7"/>ſhes, and to the creeping things, and to the grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing things, and laſt of all, to man; Bring forth: hee brought foorth all things, that all thinges might bring forth to man, and therefore expecteth that man ſhould bring forth to him; and as in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer birth he hath taken care to bring forth to vs, So in the latter and better birth he hath vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed to bring vs forth, for God is our Father, the Church his Spouſe our mother to conceiue vs his word the ſeede the meanes to beget vs:<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.3. Gal. 4.26.</note> his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite the ſoule and life to quicken vs:<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.23. Epheſ. 2.5.</note> his Miniſters the Nurſes to feede vs,<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 2.7.</note> his Goſpell the milke to nouriſh vs,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.2.</note> that ſo wee may increaſe and grow, &amp; bee able our ſelues to bring forth.</p>
            <p>The Doctrine is, that God cannot endure that any of his ſeruants be barren in Chriſtianity: <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renneſſe</hi> was a reproach among the Iewes,<note place="margin">Doctrine.</note> much more among the Gentiles: it was a naturall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach in the Law, but a more ſpirituall reproach in the Goſpell</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Plato</hi> obſerued,<note place="margin">Plato. Pieran Hierog.</note> and <hi>Pierius</hi> in his Hierogliphics, that a man is
<hi>Arbor inue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſa,</hi> a tree turned vpward, his hayre of the head the roote, his armes the branches, and ſo of the reſt; and therefore in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the godly are called trees of righteouſneſſe, and fruitfull branches,<note place="margin">Eſ.
61.3.</note> the Vinetree of the Lord: The trees in Gods Orchard,<note place="margin">Ioh. 15.2.</note> as one well obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth,<note place="margin">Eſa. 61.3.</note> are eyther <hi>Palmes</hi> or <hi>Cedars:</hi> The Palms beare fruit from their firſt growth: the Cedars though they bud long before they beare fruit, yet bring forth beautifull fruit: That which Saint <hi>Auſten</hi> in
<pb facs="tcp:15624:7"/>his 44. Homily <hi>de Sanctis</hi> obſerueth of
<hi>Mary</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> may I obſerue of the <hi>Palme</hi> and
<hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar; De ſterili ſeruus, de virgine dominus, de ſterili vox de virgine verbum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auſten. Hom. de Sanct.
<hi>44</hi>
               </note> the ſeruant <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> was borne of a barren woman: IESVS the Sauiour of a Virgine, the voice by a barren woman, the word by a Virgine: <hi>Mary</hi> was as a <hi>Palme, Elizabeth</hi> as a
<hi>Cedar.</hi> Neuer ſuch a Palme, but many ſuch Cedars; <hi>Sara</hi> barren, and yet the mother of <hi>Iſaack, Rebecca</hi> barren, yet the mother of <hi>Iacob, Rachei</hi> bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren, yet the mother of <hi>Beniamin: Manoa</hi> barren, yet the mother of <hi>Sampſon: Hanna</hi> barren, yet the mother of
<hi>Samuel, Elizabeth</hi> barren, yet the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> the Father of my Text</p>
            <p>More bleſſed are theſe barren then they that had many children. <hi>Iſaack</hi> the Heyre apparant of the Promiſe, <hi>Iacob</hi> the Supplanter, little <hi>Beniamin</hi> the Patriarch, <hi>Sampſon</hi> the ſtrong, <hi>Samuel</hi> the Seer, <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> a Prophet, and more then a Prophet: all of them moſt Honourable in their generation, the ſeed of the barren, and yet many of them were ſent to ſow the barren world; yea, and out of the ſeede of the barren, <hi>Iſaacks</hi> ſeede became as the ſtarres of Heauen, or the ſand of the Sea, and all Nations of the earth were bleſſed in his ſeed.</p>
            <p>The Eagles Embleme is <hi>ſublimius</hi> to flye lof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier, euen to behold the Sunne, as <hi>Plinie</hi> noteth, the Sunnes Embleme is
<hi>celerius</hi> ſwifter,<note place="margin">Ald. Emb. Sotinus. Pſal.
<hi>19.</hi>
               </note> the Gyant refreſhed to runne his courſe as
<hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeaketh. The Wheate in the Goſpell hath this Embleme,
<hi>perfectius</hi> riper; Firſt the Blade, then the eare,
<pb facs="tcp:15624:8"/>then full corne. <hi>Ezechiels</hi> Emblem is
<hi>profundius,</hi> dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per firſt to the ancles,<note place="margin">Marke
4.28.</note> then to the knees,<note place="margin">Ezec. 47.4.</note> then to the thighs:<note place="margin">Luke 14.10.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſtes</hi> Emblem was
<hi>Superius,</hi> ſit vp higher: <hi>Carolus Quintus</hi> Embleme was
<hi>vlierius,</hi> Goe on further, the woman with child, hath this Embleme,
<hi>plenius</hi> fuller, vntill ſhe bring forth: and ſo ought e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Chriſtian that is not drie and hardened and barren, and withered, to mount loftier with the <hi>Eagle,</hi> to runne ſwifter with the <hi>Sunne,</hi> to grow riper with the <hi>Wheate,</hi> to wade deeper with <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiel,</hi> to ſit vp higher with the <hi>Gueſt,</hi> to paſſe on further with the
<hi>Emperour,</hi> to waxe fuller with the <hi>Woman,</hi> that ſo they may bring foorth fruite in due ſeaſon. Many are long in bringing forth fruit, they are as long barren as any.</p>
            <p>The world hath expected <hi>Elephantinum Partum,</hi> and yet when it hath beene brought forth,<note place="margin">Horatius.</note> 
               <hi>Partu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riunt montes; naſcetur ridiculus mus,</hi> The beſt deede that euer they did, was that they died, and ſo the world was rid of ſuch drie, empty, windy, bare, barren, dead, withered, hardened Tenants, who neuer did good, or had any mind of goodneſſe.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Spouſe</hi> in the Canticles is moued to come away, for the Figge-tree ſayeth Chriſt hath brought forth her young figges: neuer did any tree bring forth better fruites then the Figge-tree, and neuer did any tree bring forth worſe fruits then the Fig-tree. The good fruit was
<hi>Zacheus,</hi> who climbed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a tree, that from a tree he might behold Chriſt, who was to ſuffer on a tree, for mans ſaluation, this fig-tree bare moſt pretious fruite, euen ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:15624:8"/>as Chriſt himſelfe vouchſafed to plucke, a happy tree that bare ſuch precious fruite as <hi>Zacheus</hi> was, but thriſe happy <hi>Zacheus,</hi> that ſo happily climbed on that happy tree: the tree brought forth <hi>Zache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, Zacheus</hi> brought forth a confeſſion, the tree ſuch fruit, that fruit ſuch faith, that Chriſt profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, this day is Saluation come vnto this houſe,<note place="margin">Luke. 19.9.</note> foraſmuch as he is alſo becomme a Sonne of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham.</hi> Hee that could haue rayſed out of the ſtones ſonnes to <hi>Abraham,</hi> hath raiſed out of a wild figge-tree a ſonne vnto <hi>Abraham:</hi> heere was the good fruit of the Figge-tree. For the bad fruit, the <hi>Rabbins</hi> affirm that the tree in Paradiſe from which <hi>Adam,</hi> &amp; <hi>Eue</hi> tooke the forbidden fruit was a figge tree: and many hold that the tree that
<hi>Iudas</hi> han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged himſelfe on was a fig tree, as <hi>Iuuencus</hi> the Poet teſtifieth;
<q>
                  <l>Exorſuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſuas Laqueo ſibi ſumere poenas,</l>
                  <l>Informem rapuit ficus de vertice mortem.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And to theſe wee may ioyne, that God curſed no tree but the figge tree.<note place="margin">Mald. in. <hi>27.</hi> Math.</note> It was an inhumane ſpeech of <hi>Timon,</hi> when hee ſaw a woman hanging on a figge-tree that had hanged her ſelfe, he wiſht that all trees might beare ſuch fruit: it had beene a ſpeech ſauouring of humanity to haue ſaid as Chriſt ſaid of the figge-tree, neuer ſuch fruit grow on thee more.</p>
            <p>The vſe of the <hi>Doctrine</hi> is to moue vs that wee bee not vnfruitfull in the worke of the Lord:<note place="margin">The Vſe.</note> hath God ſo cared for vs and planted and watered, and dreſſed, and hedged vs in: The word, the ſeed ſo
<pb facs="tcp:15624:9"/>oft falling: <hi>Chriſt</hi> the ſon of righteouſneſſe ſo oft ſhining, the dew of Heauen, <hi>Manna,</hi> ſo oft ſhedding, the holy ſpirite the winde ſo often blowing, and yet ſhall wee remaine dead, drie, barren, hardned, withered and accurſed Trunkes? In the Goſpell of <hi>Luke</hi> you may obſerue the Parable of the figge tree in the Vineyeard,<note place="margin">Luke 13.6.</note> which did not bring foorth; hee came and ſought fruit and found none, then ſaid behold this three yeares haue I come and ſought fruit of this figge-tree, and finde none; cut it downe why keepeth it the ground barren?</p>
            <p>I know that ſome of the Fathers interprete it onely of the Synagogue of the Iewes, and ſo that the three yeares wherein Chriſt expected fruit,<note place="margin">Greg. Hom. <hi>31</hi> in Euang.</note> were the three times 1. before the Law, 2. in the Law, 3. after the Lawe, as
<hi>Gregory</hi> on the 31. Homily on the Goſpell,<note place="margin">Ambr. in Luk. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> or the three Lawes, the firſt Naturall, the ſecond written by <hi>Moſes,</hi> the third Euangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call by Chriſt, as
<hi>Ambroſe</hi> vpon the 13. of <hi>Luke,</hi> or the three gouernements of the Iewes, the firſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the High Prieſts,<note place="margin">Theoph. in La. can. Atb. q. <hi>16</hi>
               </note> the ſecond vnder Iudges, the third vnder Kings as <hi>Euth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mias</hi> on that Goſpel ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth, But <hi>Theophilact</hi> and
<hi>Athanaſius</hi> and Saint <hi>Baſil</hi> doe expound it more largely,<note place="margin">Baſil. Br. in Jſ. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> to ſignifie the three ages of Men, Childhood, youth, and old age, and that the Lord doth look &amp; expect fruit in euery one of theſe yeares, in euery one of theſe States, &amp; when hee hath expected againe and againe, then hee proceedeth to that fearefull ſentence: Cut it down why keepeth it the ground barren.</p>
            <p>It was the 21. of March this preſent Moneth as
<pb facs="tcp:15624:9"/>
               <hi>Maldonat</hi> on the Goſpell obſerueth,<note place="margin">Maldonat.</note> that Chriſt the way ſeeing a figge tree in the way, he came to it and found nothing thereon, and then ſaid, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer fruit grow on thee henceforth. Chriſt the way is yet in the way,<note place="margin">Mat. 21.19.</note> he knoweth <hi>your ſitting downe and your riſing vppe, hee vnderſtandeth your thoughtes, for hee is about your pathes, and about your beds,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 139.1</note>
               <hi>and ſpieth out all your wayes, and wordes and works and thoughts.</hi> If he ſhould come as he hath often come, and find no fruits in many of vs, O how terrible would that ſentence be. <hi>Neuer</hi> beare henceforth;
<hi>Neuer?</hi> no <hi>Neuer,</hi> neither in this world, nor in the world to come, <hi>Neuer</hi> to bring foorth any more, Reape ye ſhal, but bring forth ye ſhall not; but yee ſhall reape the fruit of iudgement, of puniſhment: other fruit neuer bring foorth ſinne henceforth: <hi>Neuer</hi> any more, deade trees cut off from the land of the liuing, deade branches cut off from the tree of life. It was a lamentable complaint that the mother of
<hi>Tobias</hi> made for her ſonne Thou light of our eyes, ſtaffe of our age, comfort of our life, hope of our poſterity, al the ioy that we had was in thee, &amp; haue we forſaken thee? But it will be a more lamentable ſorrow when the wicked ſhall find they haue forſaken all the hope and ioy &amp; comfort and light and happines of him: But I come to the 2. part.</p>
            <p>Not buds or bloſſoms or flowres,<note place="margin">2.
<hi>Part.</hi>
               </note> or flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes but fruites: GOD doth not ſo much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect Adiectiues as Aduerbes as the Canoniſt teacheth, and God doth not loue Flowers,<note place="margin">Canoniſts.</note> ſo much as fruit, as my Text proueth. The Spouſe in the
<pb facs="tcp:15624:10"/>Canticles had Roſes &amp; Lillies, but (except that one Roſe of the fielde, and one Lillie of the Valley) ſhee prayſeth the Pomegranates and Vines, Figs and Grapes, and Oliues and Camphire, and Spike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard, and Cynamon and Saffron, and Incenſe and Aloes. Shee had her flouriſhing Garden of Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, but ſhee had alſo her fruitfull Garden of nuts, and Apples and Pomegranates. In all the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture I read but of one Flowre that is prayſed, and that Roſe from the roote of <hi>Ieſſe,</hi> ſprung in the Vallyes,<note place="margin">Cant. 2.2.</note> and grew among thornes, and flouriſhed in the Winter, and withered in the Spring, and was the moſt fragrant flower that euer grew. It was the Lilly among Thornes: A flower not eaſily to bee gathered: for we muſt vndergo much labour and ſmart if wee will enioy it: the Head thereof is crowned with Thornes, the Heart is pierced with a Speare.<note place="margin">Anſten.</note> the hands and feete ſtrucke through with Nailes: It is a Lilly among thorns. From the flowre we haue receiued fruit, and to this Flower we conſecrate all our fruit, not leaues of good profeſſion, not bloſſomes of good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, nor branches of great ſemblances, but fruit, for as of falſe prophets, ſo of true profeſſors, Chriſt hath ſpoken, <hi>Ex fructibus eorum cognoſcetis eos,</hi> yee ſhall know them by their fruites.</p>
            <p>There may be trees without branches, and bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches without fruites, but branches growing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a tree are more ſtrange. Chriſt came into the world to find fruite, and when he came to <hi>Icruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> the Iewes preſented him with branches, and
<pb facs="tcp:15624:10"/>cryed <hi>Hoſanna,</hi> but the branches had no fruites, for they ſoone ſhewed how vainely, variable the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of men are conſtant only in inconſtancy, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting in nothing, but in change, for they who had cryed <hi>Hoſanna</hi> in the higheſt, doe ſhortly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter cry let him be crucified,<note place="margin">Bernard.</note> they who ſaluted him for their King, doe preſently proteſt they haue no King but <hi>Caeſar:</hi> they who met him with Oliue bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ches, do preſently after preſent him with ſwords and ſtaues, they who ſpread their garments be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, doe after deſpoile him of his garmentes, they who adore him for the Sonne of God, after preferre <hi>Barrabas</hi> an Aſſacinate before him. Theſe were branches deceiuing, ſtealing, fading, flattering, fawning, vaniſhing branches: teaching for euer thoſe that haue ſuch branches carried before them, to contemne the baſe and mutable breath of that Monſter the multitude, neuer coueting their iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, neuer truſting their affection, neuer belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing their opinion, but as the body remaineth one, although the ſhadow bee at one time long, at ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time ſhort; ſo the Soule retaine the ſame conſtancy both in the ſweet gale of the applauſe of men, and in the bitter blaſts of their opprobrious outrage, let the ſtorme root vp ſhrubbes but not Cedars, let the winde toſſe chaffe but not wheate, and let vaine, eyther honour or infamy moue no man, who is not eyther light or weak; let no noble ſpirit bee ſeruile in caring for the prayſe, or fearing the vniuſt diſprayſe of <hi>vulgar ſhallow braines,</hi> if they be put vpon him, let him reſiſt the one with mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty,
<pb facs="tcp:15624:11"/>vndergoe the other with grauity, neuer being ſo carefull what the world will ſay of him, as what God wil ſay to him, when the world ſhall bee at an end: for the prayſes of the world be but branches.</p>
            <p>I haue ſtaide too long on theſe <hi>fruitleſſe branches,</hi> yet I hope you haue receiued ſome fruit in knowing them to be fruitleſſe.</p>
            <p>God regardeth not the tree without branches, and yet not the branches without fruit: he hath planted a <hi>Vine</hi> in euery one, the branches of this Vine are the faculties of the Soule, they muſt bring forth flowers vnto him, namely good Deſires, they muſt bring forth fruit vnto him,<note place="margin">Ariſt.</note> euen good works; the tongue to prayſe him, the feet to follow him, the eares to heare him, the hands to bee lifted vp to him, the knees to bee bowed to him, the eyes to be bedewed to him, the vnderſtanding alwayes to contemplate on him, the memory alwayes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member him, the wil to delight in him, the deſire to affect him, the ſoule to be enflamed and enfolded in the flames of his loue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> ſpake to the Phariſies, who were moſt glorious in flouriſhes but wanted fruits; O that hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie had ended in them, and not deſcended to our times. It was a hereditary diſeaſe to the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, it is no leſſe to vs, they had the voyce of <hi>Iacob,</hi> but the hands of <hi>Eſau,</hi> feathers of the Eagle, but the wings of the Oſtrich, they had the habite of ſheepe, but the diſpoſition of Wolues,<note place="margin">Plut. I. ac. Apo.</note> like the Muſitians that <hi>Diogenes</hi> taxed, they had care of tuning their inſtruments, not their minds, like vnto Copper
<pb facs="tcp:15624:11"/>which had <hi>colorem, non valorem auri,</hi> like Great peeces of Ordinance in the time of Peace, they had the faſhion but lacked their charge. They were the Maſters, the Players, the Painters, the Tyre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers, the Viſard-makers of their time, they were the Images, Semblances, Pictures, Statues, Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes &amp; Sepulchres of their times, empty clouds, windy Pipes, voide Tentes, tinckling Cymbals, drie Ceſterns of their time. They beare flowers but not fruites.</p>
            <p>The Spouſe in the Canticles inuiteth her welbelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued not onely to come to her garden,<note place="margin">Cant. 4.16.</note> but alſo to come and eate of the fruites.<note place="margin">Pſal. 102.</note> The Angels in hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen, not onely ſung the prayſes of God, but alſo doe the will, the will of God.<note place="margin">Reucl. 1.</note> The bleſſing in the Reuelation, is not onely made to thoſe that reade and heare, but to thoſe that keepe the words of that Booke. S. <hi>Iohn</hi> commaundeth to loue, not only in word and in tongue,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.</note> but alſo in deede and in truth.</p>
            <p>The Doctrine, That the true Profeſſors of the true faith are diſcerned by their liuely and effectuall workes. <hi>Exfructibus corum</hi> is the Note, mark,<note place="margin">Doctrine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and Cubite of the Sanctuarie for the good and bad. The high Prieſts garment had <hi>Pomegranates</hi> as well as <hi>Bels:</hi> The Sieling of the Temple had <hi>Palmes</hi> as well as
<hi>Chaines;</hi> The Cherubims had <hi>Wings</hi> as well as <hi>Feete;</hi> The fountaines of Lebanon had <hi>Pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers</hi> as well as
<hi>Ceſternes;</hi> The Spouſe had <hi>Vines</hi> as well as
<hi>Lillies,</hi> and her Pomegranates had <hi>Fruites</hi> as well as
<hi>Flower,</hi> and faith muſt haue a <hi>Nature</hi> as well
<pb facs="tcp:15624:12"/>as a <hi>Name,</hi> we can neuer diuide luſtre from this <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond,</hi> light from this <hi>Sunne,</hi> life from this
<hi>Soule,</hi> heat from this <hi>Fire,</hi> flowing from this <hi>Sea.</hi> The true ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of God may bee found with <hi>Abraham</hi> wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, with
<hi>Dauid</hi> running, with <hi>Iacob</hi> wreſtling, with <hi>Paul</hi> following, with the wiſe <hi>Virgins</hi> watching, the good Seruants working, with the good Tree bearing fruites.</p>
            <p>The conflict betweene vs and our aduerſaries about Faith and fruites hath beene much, they in to much aduancing them, ſome of vs too much ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuating them, they ſo earneſt for fruites, that lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle leſſe then blaſphemouſly they affirme that they deſerue Saluation: We ſo negligent in fruites, that to doe a good worke, we think it ſuperſtition, they ſo much hanging on the branches, wee ſo much rooting at the roote, as if wee would ſue out a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorce betweene Faith and Fruites, neither of vs looking to the moiſture of the roote or branches. When we ſee good works, we muſt acknowledge them to bee fruites,<note place="margin">Auſten.</note> and fruites, that wee muſt beare vpon paine of damnation, and yet to bee but fruites: we muſt ſeeke out the root of them, and when wee haue the roote, we muſt haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the moiſture and iuyce whereby it is nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed: for as the fruites of the earth grow from the roote, and that roote liueth and hath vegetation, not by it ſelfe, but is fedde and preſerued by the fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the ſoile, warmth of the Sunne, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite of the ayre vnder which it ſtandeth: ſo good works grow from faith, and that faith liueth in the
<pb facs="tcp:15624:12"/>obiect; the merites and obedience of Ieſus Chriſt, feeding and ſtrengthing it ſelfe, by the ſweet influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and ſappe of thoſe diuine dewes of Mediati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that in him wee liue, in him we grow, in him wee are grafted, in him wee flouriſh, in him we fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie: for without him, though wee ſhould wiſh to be as righteous as <hi>Noah,</hi> as obedient as <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> as holy as <hi>Iob,</hi> as faithfull as
<hi>Dauid,</hi> as deuout as <hi>Daniel,</hi> as zealous as <hi>Elias,</hi> as cleare as the Sun, or pure as the ſtarres, yet our fruits were not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable, nay not tollerable in his ſight, hauing no opinion of our own wiſedom, no hope in our own works, nor wiſedome in our power.</p>
            <p>The vſe of this Doctrine is to contemn the folly of thoſe that thinke that a bare and barren Faith will ſerue without any fruites or effect:<note place="margin">Doctrine.</note> eyther the froſt of deuotion, or the feare of the hate of ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, or the wind of contention hath blowne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way our fruits.<note place="margin">Ientilet.</note> It was an obſeruation of <hi>Ientilet</hi> vpon the Monks of his time, that their Faſts were very fat, and their prayers very leane: I cannot ſay ſo of our Faith that it is fat, but I am ſure our fruits are very leane, like to
<hi>Pharaohs</hi> withered thinne bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted cares, that it is a wonder that the leane, ſtarued carkaſſe of faith hath ſo long continued.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Luther</hi> gaue a good note to this purpoſe,<note place="margin">Luther.</note> that faith ought <hi>pingueſcere operibus,</hi> to waxe fat with fruites; but alas fruites bee as leane as faith. In times paſt ſaith wrought miracles, and remoued mountains, ſo may it yet, if it were true, for our ſinnes that are as mountaines, would be remoued
<pb facs="tcp:15624:13"/>as farre as the Eaſt is from the weſt, but faith hath wrought a more prodigious wonder, like the leane Kine that deuoured the fatte Kine; our bare pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of faith hath eaten vppe the rich Almes and fruites, and works, and deedes of mercy.</p>
            <p>A miſery it is to ſee, that there bee no fruites to bee gathered, but onely the fruits of ſinne, and that whereas vertue and goodneſſe can take no roote, ſinne beginneth in the buddes of infirmity, and by little and little ſtealeth to the fruits of negligence, and being increaſed and watered by cuſtome, it groweth to be the ſtout tree of contempt, which will rather breake then bend to any inſtruction. Surely beloued, this is not the cauſe why God hath ſo planted and watered, and kept and dreſſed his Vineyeard: theſe bee not the rootes, the plantes, the branches, the ſprigges, the buds, the bloſſoms, the flouriſhes, the field: fruits worthy amendment of life, And ſo I come to the laſt part.</p>
            <p>Not branches, for the Iewes bare branches,<note place="margin">Part.
3.</note> yet were accurſed, not flowers for the flower periſheth, and the grace thereof withereth: not leaues for the figge-tree had leaues and yet was not bleſſed; not fruit for the Phariſies bare fruit, and yet that fruit was deſpiſed: their fruit was like to that fruit which groweth where
<hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah</hi> ſtood,<note place="margin">Ioſephus.</note> faire and beautifull to the eye, but being touched they diſſolue to a ſulphurous and vaporus fume, more odious to the ſmell, then they were pleaſant to the ſight. S. <hi>Iohn</hi> therefore maketh difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene fruites, fruites worthy of amendment of life;
<pb facs="tcp:15624:13"/>in other things there is a differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce as alſo in fruits,<note place="margin">I er. 1.7.</note> there is a pure and freſh Doctrine;<note place="margin">Math. 16 6.</note> there is a ſowre and leauened doctrine;<note place="margin">Mat. 9.7</note> there is a new wine of the Goſpell; and there is a mixt wine of <hi>Babylon:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu.
17.4.</note> there are wholeſome words:<note place="margin">2. Tim.
1.13.</note> There are vnwholeſome words: there is a Doctrine of God,<note place="margin">Eph. 4.29.</note> there is a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Diuels:<note place="margin">Ioh. 7.16.</note> and there is a guiding word,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.1.</note> and a fretting word:<note place="margin">Gal.
5.22</note> fruites of the fleſh, and fruites of the ſpirit: worthy and vnworthy fruites. <hi>Leſbian</hi> vines be more honored by
<hi>Ariſtole</hi> then the vines of <hi>Rhodes:</hi> for vnder that Parable hee alludeth to ſucceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his ſchoole, choſing rather
<hi>Theophraſtus</hi> born at <hi>Leſbos,</hi> then <hi>Menedemus</hi> born at <hi>Rhodes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aul. Gel. N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct. Att lib. <hi>13.5.</hi>
               </note> there was ſome compariſon betweene them, for they were both good. But theſe fruites that I ſpeake of, bee as contrary as light and darkeneſſe, the Northerne and Southerne Poles not ſo Diame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trally oppoſed the one againſt the other, as theſe fruites of the fleſh and Spirit: Nor the compariſon of Tares eating vp the Wheate, Eagles feathers conſuming all other feathers;
<hi>Moſes</hi> Serpentes deuouring the Enchanters, and Arke demoliſhing Dagon.</p>
            <p>There are all kinds of fruit, &amp; all colours of fruit in euill, the greene fruites of vnperfectneſſe, the yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low fruit of Gall and bitterneſſe, the redde fruit of blood and cruelneſſe, the tawny and Morian fruite of ſinful deformedneſſe, the Skie colour change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able fruit of vnſtaiedneſſe, the Leopard ſpotted fruit of vnholines, the bluſh colour fruit of prophaneſſe, and the redde colour fruit of drunkenneſſe, the pale
<pb facs="tcp:15624:14"/>colour fruit of vncleanneſſe, the flame colour truit of blaſphemous wickedneſſe, they haue many co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, by the which they may bee knowen, yet but onely one taſte; They are for the moſt part bitter ſweete, bad trees and bad fruite, <hi>Concupiſcence</hi> is the roote, <hi>Conſent</hi> the trunke, <hi>Bad deſires</hi> the braun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,
<hi>Lewde words</hi> the buds, <hi>Vile actions</hi> the flowers, <hi>Lewde cuſtomes</hi> the fruites, <hi>Sathan</hi> did plant, <hi>Sugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion</hi> did water, <hi>Continuance</hi> in ſinnne doth increaſe them,
<hi>Neceſsitie</hi> in ſinne doth ripen them, <hi>Iudgement</hi> doth gather them, and <hi>Hell</hi> doth burne them: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they bee not fruites worthy amendement of life.</p>
            <p>That you may know them both, in the fifth to the <hi>Gallat.</hi>
22. you may take a ſuruey of them both; <hi>The fruites of the fleſh are Adulterie, Fornication, Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal.
5.21.</note> 
               <hi>Wantonneſſe, Idolatrie, Witchcraft, Hatred, Debate, Emulation, Wrath, Contentions, Seditions, Hereſies, Enuie, Murthers, Drunkenneſſe, Gluttonie,</hi> and ſuch like. <hi>The fruites of the ſpirit are Loue, Peace, Long ſuffering, Gentleneſſe, Goodneſſe, Faith, Meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Temperance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The forbidden fruit of Paradiſe proued accurſed, but the fruit of that fruit more accurſed, ſo the fruits of the fleſh bee moſt hatefull and fearefull, but the fruites of thoſe fruites exceede.
<hi>Pride</hi> is a fruit of the fleſh, but the fruit of the fruit exceedeth: It blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the eyes, darkneth the minde, deceiueth the vnderſtanding, depriueth the reaſon, diſguiſeth the countenance, maketh the proude man in the ſight of men a foole, in the ſight of God a Diuell. The
<pb facs="tcp:15624:14"/>fruit of this fruit thruſt the Angels out of heauen, ouerthrewe the Tower of <hi>Babel,</hi> confounded the <hi>Tongues,</hi> drowned <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> depriued <hi>Saul,</hi> hanged <hi>Haman,</hi> ſlew
<hi>Baltaſher,</hi> changed <hi>Nebucadonoſor</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a beaſt.
<hi>Luxurie</hi> is the fruit of the fleſh, but the fruit of this fruit bringeth polution before God, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe before men, filthineſſe to the body, rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenneſſe to the bones, it burnt <hi>Sodome,</hi> ſlew the
<hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chemites,</hi> deſtroyed the <hi>Beniamites,</hi> curſed
<hi>Ruben,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiled <hi>Dauid,</hi> betrayed <hi>Sampſon,</hi> deceiued
<hi>Salomon.</hi> Enuie is the fruit of the fleſh, but the fruit of that fruite excelleth it, it puniſheth it ſelfe, fretteth the heart, ſhortneth the life, eateth the fleſh, conſumeth the Spirit, turneth a man into a Dogge, a Chriſtian into a Diuel, it made <hi>Caine</hi> enuie <hi>Abels</hi> ſanctitie, <hi>Rachel Leahs</hi> faecunditie, <hi>Saul Dauids</hi> felicitie,
<hi>Sathan</hi> mans innocencie, <hi>Haman Mordecaies</hi> honeſtie; the
<hi>Phariſees</hi> Chriſts heauenly Dietie. Drunkenneſſe is a fruite of the fleſh, but the fruite of this fruite ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth: It confoundeth the braine, conſumeth the body, drowneth the iudgement, ſtealeth away the ſenſe, witte, memorie, health, credit, friends and all; And hath ouerthrowne not onely many thouſand particular men, but many great Houſes, Families, Cities, Countreyes, Nations, Generations, for this laſt ſinne is more preſumed vpon, then almoſt any other; for ſince that God made that promiſe, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer more to <hi>drowne the world, the world hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt drowned themſelues by this beaſtly, vgly, monſtrous, loathſome Inundation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Doctrine,<note place="margin">Doctrine.</note> that good works muſt be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily
<pb facs="tcp:15624:15"/>performed, or elſe they bee not fruits worthy: The difference between <hi>digna</hi> and <hi>digne</hi> is much:<note place="margin">Arte Aethick. Juſtus, Juſta, Iuſte.</note> many doe worthy workes but not worthily: and therefore it is not to bring <hi>Digna</hi> worthy fruites, which vnworthy men may vnworthily doe, but God alſo requireth,
<hi>dignus, digna, digne,</hi> the name of goodneſſe in the doer, the rules of goodneſſe in the things done, and the end of goodnes in the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for
<hi>Caine</hi> offered, <hi>Simon Magus</hi> beleeued, <hi>Herod</hi> liſtened, <hi>Foelix</hi> feared, <hi>Saul</hi> obeyed, <hi>Iezabel</hi> faſted, the <hi>Phariſies</hi> prayed, theſe were worthy fruites, but not worthily performed. There may be a zeale without knowledge, aknowledge with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out conſcience, a loue without Holineſſe, a Prayer without Faith, a Faith without fruites, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe had not the <hi>Phariſies</hi> loſt ſo many Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, ſo many Faſts, ſo many watches, ſo many works, ſo many waſhings, ſo many tythings, ſo many howrs in hearing, reading, interpreting <hi>Moſes</hi> &amp; the Prophets,, otherwiſe had not the
<hi>Papiſts</hi> loſt ſo many Oriſons, ſo many obſeruations, deuotions, contritions, confeſſions, ſatisfactions, penances, pilgrimages, ſo much labour in examining their hart, chaſtening their fleſh, whipping the body, puniſhing the Soule.</p>
            <p>The fruits of <hi>Faith</hi> as all the Fathers agree, <hi>Aug. Ambr, Bernard, Ierom, Theop. Theodoret, Epiphanius,</hi> &amp; all others in their writings obſerue, are Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and good works, theſe are the fruites wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy amendment of life. <hi>Cteſias</hi> in deſcribing
<hi>India</hi> maketh mention of a tree that beſides fruites, drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth
<pb facs="tcp:15624:15"/>and diſtilleth certaine teares, of which are made pretious Amber. The true Chriſtian muſt be like this tree, his workes muſt be his fruites, his repentance his diſtilled droppes. The droppes of the Vine-tree are preſcribed againſt the Leproſie, hee that is a branch of the <hi>true Vine</hi> muſt yeelde theſe droppes againſt the Leproſie of ſinne, and ſo hee ſhall bee ſure to bring forth fruits worthy of amendment of life, though not worthy <hi>merito condigni</hi> of eternall life, yet worthy in ſome ſorte, <hi>merito congrui,</hi> of amendment of life.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Vſe.</note> The vſe hereof is, to incite you all by all the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of God, as euer you hope to ſtand before the Throne of Grace, to bring foorth at the length ſome fruites acceptable to God, profitable to men, auaileable to your owne Soules, that yee no longer turne the Grace of God into wantonneſſe, not looking vpon Faith with the eye of curioſity, but hearing with the eares and heartes of obedience, rather bringing good mindes then ſharpe wits to Sermons, that ſo Religion may no more flie in the ayre of your opinion, but be ſetled in your ſoules to fruitfull operations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> you heare crieth out for Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; a thing long prayed for and ſought for in the former Ages of Idolatry,
<hi>ſudore &amp; ſanguine</hi> with the bloud of Myriades of Martyrs. The laſt <hi>Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> performed it, but performed it ſo, as that the Cure is become as dangerous as the diſeaſe, and religion hath taken as deepe a wound in the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, as ſhee had in the deformation, for in place
<pb facs="tcp:15624:16"/>of the hypocriſie of ſeeming, there is brought in the impudency of neither beeing nor ſeeing, and to cure ſuperſtition, a neglect of deuotion, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoide the opinion of meriting, a defect of the care of well doing, to take away the ſuperfluity there is not enough left for the neceſſity of the Church, the faith which was wont to bee in words, is ſcarſe found in the oathes of men, the Doctrine of the Church not followed, the cenſures of the Church not feared. The pride and exceſſe of the Clergy taken away, and the pouerty and contempt of the Cleargy remaining; then there were woodden Prieſts, golden liuings, now golden Prieſts, wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den liuings. The Garden of the Spouſe blaſted, her trees blemiſhed, her branches withered, her fruites vaniſhed, that as hee ſaid, <hi>No feare of God;</hi> ſo I ſay, no fruite for God in the land, and yet who is not thought a Profeſſor? who is not thought re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious? It was worthily obiected to an vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy fellow in <hi>Rome,</hi> who putting on a graue coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance in the Senate was taken vp thus;<note place="margin">Plutarch.</note> 
               <hi>Quis te ferat aedificantem vt Craſſus, caenantem vt Lucullus, loquentem vt Cato:</hi> who can abide thee building vaine-gloriouſly as <hi>Craſſus,</hi> banqueting riotouſly as
<hi>Lucullus,</hi> and yet ſpeaking grauely as <hi>Cato:</hi> ſo may it bee asked, who can abide that thoſe that are as great Church-robbers as
<hi>Nabuchodonoſor,</hi> as enui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous as <hi>Haman,</hi> as riotous as
<hi>Balthazar,</hi> as proude as <hi>Herod,</hi> as diſobedient as
<hi>Corah,</hi> ſhould bee thought Religious, or ſhould offer to take the word of the Lord in their mouths, and yet hate to be reformed.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15624:16"/>
            <p>My ſpeech draweth to the cloſe. The place wherein I ſpeake repreſenteth that tree of <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſtus,</hi> which at euery time doth bud and bloſſom and beare fruit: O euer let there bee found here, ſome ripe, ſome drawing to their ripeneſſe, ſome in the flower, ſome in the bud of hope, ſome plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull in fruit: if there were no other motiues to incite this preſence, and if neither watering, plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, nor any other meanes would draw you, yet the Preſident of our <hi>young Cedar</hi> might draw all that make their neſt vnder the ſhade of his Greatneſſe, ſeeing his Highneſſe like to that YOVNG PRINCE, is increaſed <hi>in wiſedome, and ſtature,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 9.</note> 
               <hi>and fauour with God and men.</hi> It was but the ſpeech of a Poet, <hi>Exeat Aula, qui vult eſſe Pius,</hi> that Godlineſſe is no good Courtier; I hope it, and with the bended knees of my Soule pray for it, that that poſition neuer take place here, but that holineſſe may crown this houſe for euer, and that not onely in the Chappell and Cloſſetts, but that the face of godlineſſe may bee ſeene in the preſence, and the heart of goodneſſe attend the inmoſt Priuy Chambers, &amp; that euery one here may in euery action both pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like and priuate yeeld a ſauour of God, and a taſte of godlineſſe, <hi>and bring forth fruites in due ſeaſon, fruites worthy amendme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of life,</hi> that ſo this Court <hi>may bring forth encreaſe, and God euen our own God may giue vs his bleſsing, yea God may bleſſe v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and we all: and the endes of the world may feare him, and we may yeeld Glorit to the Father, and to the Sonne and to the holy Ghoſt, as it was in the beginning, both now and euer, world without end.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
